<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-08-14T11:02:58-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">Team day</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/07/team-day.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Team day" /><published>2025-08-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-08-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/08/07/team-day</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/07/team-day.html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week, <a href="https://design-history.prevention-services.nhs.uk/screening-invite/">team Invite</a> got together for a bit of team building and to talk about our evolving remit.</p>

<p>As a team who are located all across the country, it’s the first time since I joined the project that we’ve all been able to get together in person.</p>

<p>I can’t speak for everyone else, but I really enjoyed the day. I personally value the face-to-face time with colleagues, and whilst I appreciate that being co-located is now far from the norm, I think that it’s important to make the time and space to get together, where people are willing and able to.</p>

<h2 id="less-is-more">Less is more</h2>

<p>On days like this, it’s tempting to pack out the agenda and solve <em>all the things</em>. But we purposely kept the day fairly light with an emphasis on taking time to see where conversation led us.</p>

<p>We did, however, give the day a bit of structure…</p>

<h3 id="morning-getting-to-know-each-other">Morning: getting to know each other</h3>

<p>After a relaxed start to give those who had to travel plenty of time to arrive and get settled, we ran a team retrospective. We kept it basic and allowed conversations to carry on for longer than we might’ve ordinarily.</p>

<p>I think out of all the team-y sessions, retros are the ones that I find most difficult to do remotely!</p>

<p>Some useful themes around best practice for sharing information, prioritisation of work, and cross-team collaboration emerged.</p>

<p>We then led onto a <a href="https://emilywebber.co.uk/the-team-manual-a-exercise-to-help-build-empathy-in-teams/">“manual of me”</a> exercise. I have to admit, in the past, I’d been a bit sceptical about these types of things. But now, having done it with a number of different teams, I’m 100% converted to its value.</p>

<p>I also think that it’s something worth repeating every now and then. Not only do you learn more about the people you’re working with, it’s helpful to reflect on how your needs change over time.</p>

<p>Here’s my latest ‘manual of me’.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/manual-of-me.png" alt="A screenshot of Matt's manual of me from the recent team day" /></p>

<h3 id="afternoon-our-evolving-remit">Afternoon: our evolving remit</h3>

<p>When I joined the team, our remit was focused on establishing digital 1st communications across all screening pathways (breast, cervical, bowel, etc.).</p>

<p>Our immediate priority remains the <a href="https://mattlucht.github.io/2025/08/04/where-am-i.html#what-are-we-doing">delivery of a private beta of breast screening appointment invites</a>. However, beyond that, our focus has shifted to looking at the end-to-end breast screening experience from the participant perspective, of which comms is just one part.</p>

<p>The goal of the afternoon was to put aside all known constraints (of which there are many) and imagine what might make for the best screening experience.</p>

<p>We mapped out the lifecycle of a screening participant, from pre-eligibility age to getting their first screening appointment, receiving their results, through to being over the age eligible for automatic appointments.</p>

<p>At each stage, we thought about the potential needs and opportunities where we might be able to do something different.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/team-day-wall.png" alt="A photo of the wall from the team day where we mapped out ideas about a possible screening journey" /></p>

<p>Collectively, we came up with lots of ideas and identified some areas that we’d like to explore further and talk about with other teams who are working on other aspects of the breast screening pathway.</p>

<p>As well as potential service ‘features’, it also highlighted some overarching principles, such as ensuring whatever we do must be equitable and accessible so as to not inadvertently excluded anyone from screening.</p>

<p>This week we’re back to working as a remote team and hopefully feeling the benefits of a day spent together!</p>]]></content><author><name>matt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Last week, team Invite got together for a bit of team building and to talk about our evolving remit.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Where am I?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/04/where-am-i.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Where am I?" /><published>2025-08-04T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-08-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/08/04/where-am-i</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/04/where-am-i.html"><![CDATA[<p>Earlier this year, I joined the <a href="https://www.digital-prevention-services.nhs.uk/">Digital Prevention Services Portfolio</a> (DPSP) team within the <a href="https://transform.england.nhs.uk/">transformation directorate</a> of NHS England (NHSE).</p>

<p>I’m working within <a href="https://transform.england.nhs.uk/key-tools-and-info/digital-screening/">digital screening</a>, and more specifically on how we can improve the participant experience of breast screening.</p>

<p>I’ve joined to help from a delivery perspective. When I started the team had recently gone through a number of changes of both people and scope of work. So the immediate focus was about helping to provide some stablity. Thankfully, this has settled down, and we’ve a fantastic team with a wealth of experience across public and private sectors.</p>

<h2 id="what-are-we-doing">What are we doing?</h2>
<p>Our current goal as a team is to switch from sending appointment letters through the post to a digital-first approach to communications.</p>

<p>We’re starting small with invitations for routine screening appointments within a single breast screening office. As we learn, iterate, and are able to prove the approach, we’ll explore the appropriateness of sending other types of communications digitally (appointment reminders, appointment cancellations, results, etc.), and ramp up the number of breast screening offices using our service.</p>

<p>Across England there are 76 breast screening offices; the first one that we’re going into private beta with is Birmingham.</p>

<iframe src="https://www.linkedin.com/embed/feed/update/urn:li:ugcPost:7351359431512604674" height="1064" width="504" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" title="Embedded post"></iframe>

<h2 id="considerations">Considerations</h2>

<h3 id="language-and-messaging">Language and messaging</h3>
<p>Breast screening can be a sensitive topic for many people, often with preconceptions, especially for those who are being invited for the first time.</p>

<p>We recently conducted some user research with first-time attendees, and while most people understood the importance of getting screened, there were a mix of concerns that might affect their willingness to attend an appointment. These concerns included things like screening being painful or uncomfortable, body confidence, and accessibility needs.</p>

<p>Another consideration we face when thinking about how we communicate is that traditionally breast screening participants are referred to solely as “women”. We want to make sure that the language we use is as inclusive as possible and that everyone eligible, regardless of how they identify, is made to feel welcome and that screening is for them.</p>

<h3 id="technology">Technology</h3>
<p>On the surface, sending invitations might seem straightforward, but like anything, when you look under the hood, it can get a bit more complicated.</p>

<p>To identify which invitations to send, we need to extract appointment data from the <a href="https://www.nbss.nhs.uk/">National Breast Screening Service</a> (NBSS), an application that is older than some members of the team! We then have to consider how best to process and distribute personally identifiable data in a secure way. Finally, we need to have a robust way to track who we sent invitations to and when they were sent.</p>

<h3 id="ensuring-clinical-safety">Ensuring clinical safety</h3>
<p>Understandably, there is a huge importance to ensure that everything that we do is clinically safe. At NHSE there is a robust process that we need to follow, and one that I’m very much still learning about! There’s probably a blog post or two about how we’re collaborating with assurance colleagues, and in particular how we’re making this work within an agile delivery environment!</p>

<p>…there are so many opportunities to make an impact to people’s attitudes and experiences towards screening. I’m exicted to get stuck in!</p>]]></content><author><name>matt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Earlier this year, I joined the Digital Prevention Services Portfolio (DPSP) team within the transformation directorate of NHS England (NHSE).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First post in a while</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/02/first-note-in-a-while.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First post in a while" /><published>2025-08-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-08-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/08/02/first-note-in-a-while</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/02/first-note-in-a-while.html"><![CDATA[<p>Inspired by friends and colleagues at NHSE England, I thought that I’d start trying to write some week(ish) notes again.</p>

<p>Primarily this is a place for me to write down some of my thoughts – I find it useful as a way of thinking about the work that we’re doing, challenges we’re facing and ways that we’ve tackled problems. Obviously not everything is suitable for being public, but I’ll aim to be as open as I can!</p>

<p>I wasn’t sure where to put them, so decided to spin up a basic <a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub pages</a> site and mess about with <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a>. I got distracted and this took me longer than expected, so I’ve kinda run out of time to write a proper post today.</p>

<p>To get me going I’ve cheated a bit and added a couple of posts from a previous project so that this isn’t entirely empty. Previous weeknotes can be found on the <a href="https://digital-land.github.io/weeknote/">Digital Land</a> where I contributed to them with the rest of the team.</p>]]></content><author><name>matt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Inspired by friends and colleagues at NHSE England, I thought that I’d start trying to write some week(ish) notes again.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Digging into local area requirements</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/01/22/digging-into-local-area-requirements.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Digging into local area requirements" /><published>2024-01-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-01-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/01/22/digging-into-local-area-requirements</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/01/22/digging-into-local-area-requirements.html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This was originally posted on the <a href="https://digital-land.github.io/blog-post/digging-into-local-area-requirements/">Digtial Land blog</a></em></p>

<p>Recently we’ve been spending a bit of time looking into local area requirements (also referred to as validation lists, checklists, and a few other names too). We hope that through understanding more about these requirements we’ll be able to better prioritise our work in data standards to support the modern planning software and local plan projects.</p>

<h2 id="local-area-requirements-what-are-they">Local area requirements, what are they?</h2>

<p>Local area requirements are typically a document (or sometimes a webpage) published by a local planning authority that lists all of the <em>things</em> you’ll need to provide when making a planning application.</p>

<p>The <em>‘things’</em> are usually assessments or reports – such as an <a href="https://www.gov.uk/guidance/air-quality--3#what-is-the-role-of-plan-making-with-regard-to-air-quality">air quality assessment</a> or a <a href="https://www.camden.gov.uk/daylight-and-sunlight-assessment">daylight and sunlight assessment</a> – and are required based on certain sets of circumstances. For example, a <a href="https://www.camden.gov.uk/heritage-statements">heritage statement</a> needs to be provided for any works that affect a <a href="https://www.planning.data.gov.uk/dataset/listed-building">listed building</a>, <a href="https://www.planning.data.gov.uk/dataset/locally-listed-building">locally listed building</a> or <a href="https://www.planning.data.gov.uk/dataset/conservation-area">conservation area</a>.</p>

<p>As the name suggests, what you need to provide and the circumstances under which you need to provide it can vary from local planning authority to local planning authority.</p>

<h2 id="why-do-we-think-theyre-interesting">Why do we think they’re interesting?</h2>

<h3 id="triggers-and-rules">Triggers and rules</h3>

<p>Through analysing the local area requirements we hope to document what planning considerations trigger what <a href="https://digital-land.github.io/data-standards/what-we-are-working-on/planning-consideration/">planning requirements</a>. We can then build up a picture of what considerations occur most frequently and based on that we’re hypothesising that making these available as data would help unlock greater value in the data available on <a href="https://planning.data.gov.uk">planning.data.gov.uk</a>.</p>

<h3 id="consultative-data">Consultative data</h3>

<p>Similar to the triggers, we’re interested in exploring that planning considerations might be needed in order to fulfil a planning requirement. These might be things that help write a report or provide evidence to the outcome of an assessment.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/data-and-triggers.png" alt="A sketched diagram showing the relationship between triggers and datasets. Image courtesy of Mike Rose" /></p>

<h2 id="what-have-we-learnt-so-far">What have we learnt so far?</h2>

<p>…at this point we ought to mention that we’re not the first people to be looking into this area. We owe a big thank you to Emily Hadley for sharing some work that they did a while back whilst working with <a href="https://www.buckinghamshire.gov.uk/">Buckinghamshire Council</a> and also Rich and the team at <a href="https://www.camden.gov.uk/">Camden</a> for sharing an early view of their new local area requirements document.</p>

<h3 id="how-were-approaching-the-analysis">How we’re approaching the analysis</h3>

<p>We’ve been using <a href="https://airtable.com/">Airtable</a> as a starting point to help collate all the information. It allows us to easily create lists of things in different tables and then tag or link between them.</p>

<p>We begun by listing all the different planning requirements mentioned by a handful of local planning authorities and against each one recorded:</p>

<ul>
  <li>the type planning application(s) the requirement related to</li>
  <li>what planning consideration triggered the requirement</li>
  <li>which local planning authority listed the requirement</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/assets/images/local-area-requirement-analysis.png" alt="A screen shot of the planning requirement table in Airtable" /></p>

<p>If you’re interested in taking a look at the Airtable you’ll need to create an account and then request read-only access <a href="https://airtable.com/invite/l?inviteId=invlRcIOlr5syXxlx&amp;inviteToken=e2ccc363be8acab50ae87948f89560021927bf0310d9e92918391650491c6c14&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_source=product_team&amp;utm_content=transactional-alerts">here</a>.</p>

<h3 id="early-days-but-we-think-were-onto-something">Early days, but we think we’re onto something</h3>

<p>So far we’ve gathered information from 9 local planning authorities. Admittedly this is a small sample size but we intend to add to this. But already it’s feeling like we’re seeing some useful insights emerge.</p>

<p>For example, we can see that applications that relate to (or are in the proximity of) buildings of a particular use type trigger the most planning requirements. This is closely followed by conservation areas, community facilities, listed buildings and open space.</p>

<p>We can also see that from the sets of local area requirements that we’ve looked at so far that there are 11 planning requirements that are required (in certain circumstances) by all local planning authorities and that there are some planning requirements that are only requirements for certain types of authorities (so far at least).</p>

<h2 id="up-next">Up next…</h2>

<p>We’ve a couple of immediate next steps:</p>

<ul>
  <li>we want to share our approach with colleagues in planning software to see how this approach may help with what they’re doing. We’re also keen to get their take on some of the planning considerations that are emerging from this work</li>
  <li>increase the sample size of local planning requirements so that we can be more confident around emerging findings</li>
  <li>start thinking about an approach for making this information more open and available for others to view and use</li>
  <li>to help with the analysis we gathered a list of local area requirements from all local planning authorities. Its very much a snapshot in time but we plan to publish it as a dataset on planning.data.gov.uk</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>matt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This was originally posted on the Digtial Land blog]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Wrapping up the local government content design discovery project</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/03/11/wrapping-up-the-content-discovery-project.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wrapping up the local government content design discovery project" /><published>2023-03-11T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-03-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/03/11/wrapping-up-the-content-discovery-project</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/03/11/wrapping-up-the-content-discovery-project.html"><![CDATA[<p>On 9 January we kicked off the ‘local government content discovery’ project. The project was funded by the Local Government Digital Transformation Fund, and managed by the <a href="https://www.wlga.wales/home">Welsh Local Government Association</a>. The project was led by <a href="https://www.blaenau-gwent.gov.uk/en/home/">Blaenau Gwent</a> Council alongside 3 other local authorities – <a href="https://www.newport.gov.uk/splash-homepage.aspx">Newport</a>, <a href="https://www.monmouthshire.gov.uk/">Monmouthshire</a> and <a href="https://www.torfaen.gov.uk/en/Home.aspx">Torfaen</a> – and supported by the <a href="https://digitalpublicservices.gov.wales/">Centre for Digital Public Services</a>.</p>

<p>A few weeks ago I <a href="https://mattlucht.github.io/2023/02/01/local-government-content-design-discovery.html">wrote a blog post</a> about why the project came about, and the approach that we were taking with the discovery. Now as we near the end of this phase of the project we want to tell you about what we’ve learned and provide recommendations for moving into alpha.</p>

<h2 id="a-quick-recap">A quick recap</h2>
<p>It was recognised that local authorities are struggling with creating, publishing and maintaining content across the services that they provide to their residents.</p>

<p>We wanted to demonstrate the impact that this was causing, and explore opportunities to do things differently.</p>

<p>We wanted to use a real-life example as we believed that would provide the biggest impact. We chose council tax as a case study, specifically looking at <a href="https://www.gov.wales/council-tax-discounts-and-reduction/living-alone">single Person discounts</a> and <a href="https://www.gov.wales/council-tax-discounts-and-reduction/students">student exemptions</a>.</p>

<h2 id="hearing-from-users">Hearing from users</h2>
<p>In our first round of user research we spoke with 4 users from across each of the local authorities to learn about their experiences with using the existing council tax service.</p>

<p>It was particularly interesting hearing from users who had recently moved into a new property and how they went about setting up their council tax payments. We saw that when trying to apply online there was often the need to speak to someone at the local authority via email or telephone so that they could clarify details or find out the status of their council tax query.</p>

<p>It’s worth highlighting again that the goal of this discovery wasn’t to transform the council tax service, but to identify where a better approach to content design could help improve existing services.</p>

<h3 id="what-we-learnt-about-the-existing-services">What we learnt about the existing services</h3>
<p>During the user research sessions we asked participants to find out if they qualified for either a single person discount or a student exemption.</p>

<p>While some users were able to complete this task, we saw that it took alot of navigating around the local authority websites which often left them feeling the need to speak to somebody within the local authority to check.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“…i’m stressed. If I feel like this and it’s not for real, what would a person be like if they didn’t have the ability to do this and they needed to get the application in by a certain period”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We found that the language on the website was unfamiliar with users and caused confusion and uncertainty. We’ve talked about this in previous weeknotes as <a href="https://mattlucht.github.io/2023/01/20/local-government-content-discovery-week-2.html#council-speak">‘council speak’</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“I think we’ve got to the bit we’re talking about, but ‘disregarded’ that’s a strange word in my vocabulary”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“…once you’ve used the council website a couple of times you get to start thinking like they think”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It was clear that the users often relied on the support and assistance of others to help them complete tasks online and they expressed concerns that if that support wasn’t available then they’d really struggle.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“…because if [redacted] died, I’d be in real trouble because I wouldn’t know what I was doing on this computer”</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="demonstrating-improvements">Demonstrating improvements</h2>

<h3 id="building-a-prototype">Building a prototype</h3>
<p>Based on what we’d learned from the initial round of user research we wanted to explore whether we were able to improve the service through the use of clearer language, and an approach of guiding users through the service to help them understand whether they qualified for a discount or not.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://docs.publishing.service.gov.uk/repos/smart-answers.html">smart answers design pattern from GOV.UK</a> felt like a good approach and something worth testing.</p>

<p>We’ve recorded a demo of the prototype that you can watch here: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qKrvTTYN9PQ</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qKrvTTYN9PQ?si=jlrDHDi4I2MmMLIP" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h3 id="testing-a-prototype">Testing a prototype</h3>
<p>After building the prototype we ran a 2nd round of user research to help us learn whether this approach might overcome some of the challenges we identified with the service.</p>

<p>We tested the prototype with 6 users and we received positive feedback from each of the sessions. When asking them to test the same scenarios as the first round of user testing, all were able to confidently complete the journeys.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“that was quite straightforward”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>However, there is still room for improvement. By quickly prototyping and testing we were able to see where there were opportunities to further refine the content and add greater clarification. We also learned more about the service from speaking to real users, this information would be critical for a council tax transformation project.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“…maybe there’s a reason for this step, but it feels a bit bureaucratic”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You can find the <a href="https://mattlucht.github.io/2023/03/03/local-government-content-discovery-week-8.html#testing-the-prototype-with-users">high-level findings</a> from this round of user research in our weeknotes.</p>

<h3 id="iterating-the-prototype">Iterating the prototype</h3>
<p>With real users testing our prototype, we could see where we could further iterate on some of the steps and content. Due to time constraints we’ve not been able to take this into another round of user testing, but we feel it would be great if work could continue in this area after this phase of the project finishes.</p>

<h3 id="our-recommendations">Our recommendations</h3>
<p>We’ll be writing one more blog post that summaries our recommendations for next steps.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/council-tax-prototype.gif" alt="An animated gif of the council tax prototype" /></p>]]></content><author><name>matt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On 9 January we kicked off the ‘local government content discovery’ project. The project was funded by the Local Government Digital Transformation Fund, and managed by the Welsh Local Government Association. The project was led by Blaenau Gwent Council alongside 3 other local authorities – Newport, Monmouthshire and Torfaen – and supported by the Centre for Digital Public Services.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Local government content discovery – week 9</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/03/10/local-government-content-discovery-week-9.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Local government content discovery – week 9" /><published>2023-03-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-03-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/03/10/local-government-content-discovery-week-9</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/03/10/local-government-content-discovery-week-9.html"><![CDATA[<p>So this is it. The end of our final week of discovery. It’s safe to say that the past 9 weeks have flown by.</p>

<p>Our focus for this week has been around reflecting on what we’ve done, and wrapping things up to ensure that we don’t lose what we’ve learnt.</p>

<h2 id="iterating-the-prototype">Iterating the prototype</h2>

<p>Based on what we learnt through the user testing of the prototype we’ve been able to make some small iterations. We’ve not had the opportunity to test these changes in another round of research, but if this work is carried forward in the future then they’re ready to go!</p>

<p>We specifically looked at whether adding a contact preference of email or telephone would provide a more positive experience for the user. And also in the case of the student exemption journey, whether asking for either a student ID or a student certificate might test better.</p>

<p>These changes are <a href="https://council-tax.onrender.com/">live in the prototype</a> now.</p>

<h2 id="welsh-translation-of-the-prototype">Welsh translation of the prototype</h2>

<p>We also have the content for the prototype translated into Welsh. We worked with a Welsh speaker to try and ensure that when the translation happened it wasn’t a formal literal translation but something that was more intuitive.</p>

<p>At the moment the switching between languages isn’t hooked up in the hosted version of the prototype, but all the <a href="https://github.com/learnbymakingwales/council-tax-prototype/tree/cymraeg">code is in a branch on GitHub</a> ready to be used if needed.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/welsh-start-page.png" alt="A screen shot of the Welsh language start page" /></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/welsh-confirmation-page.png" alt="A screen shot of the Welsh language confirmation page" /></p>

<h2 id="writing-up-our-recommendations">Writing up our recommendations</h2>

<p>We’ve also been writing up what we’ve learnt and our recommendations. These will be published in two blog posts on the Welsh Local Government Association blog. We’ll also be cross posting them alongside our weeknotes.</p>

<p>Our recommendations are broken down into three themes:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Identify content creators who are supported and empowered to own the content</li>
  <li>Introduce some content design best practises</li>
  <li>Pick a service (or part of a service) to run a transformation alpha</li>
</ol>

<p>The blog post covers these three themes in much more detail.</p>

<h2 id="list-of-things">List of things</h2>

<p>Here’s a summary of some of the things we’ve made during discovery.</p>

<h3 id="prototype">Prototype</h3>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://council-tax.onrender.com/">Hosted version of the prototype</a></li>
  <li>Prototype <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qKrvTTYN9PQ">demo</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/learnbymakingwales/council-tax-prototype/tree/main">Latest version of the prototype code</a></li>
  <li>Code for the version of the <a href="https://github.com/learnbymakingwales/council-tax-prototype/tree/prototype-iteration-one">prototype we tested with users</a></li>
  <li>Code for <a href="https://github.com/learnbymakingwales/council-tax-prototype/tree/cymraeg">welsh language prototype</a></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="guides">Guides</h3>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://learnbymaking.wales/en/resource/content-request-forms.html">Guide for content requests</a></li>
  <li>Content design <a href="https://trello.com/b/9k38uMH8/example-content-design-triage-board">triage board</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://learnbymaking.wales/en/resource/using-a-feedback-survey.html">User feedback</a></li>
  <li>Guide for <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1-OOMO-GaA8kjL6JJ4WuZTqo_K2JMa-1damK2H5f5b4I/edit?usp=sharing">maintaining the prototype toolkit</a></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="miscellaneous">Miscellaneous</h3>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://docs.google.com/drawings/d/1Y2OwE__U3_HKJyqRTkdh8F3ElpDzkbuedjzJNTVOR-k/edit?usp=sharing">Council tax journey flows</a></li>
  <li>WLGA <a href="https://localgovernmentdigital.wales/transformation-fund/local-government-content-design-discovery/">blog post</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="thank-you">Thank you</h2>

<p>Finally, thank you to everyone who participated in this discovery. From folk within the 4 local authorities, residents who gave their time to participate in user research sessions, to everyone who attended show and tells and gave us feedback along the way.</p>]]></content><author><name>matt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[So this is it. The end of our final week of discovery. It’s safe to say that the past 9 weeks have flown by.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Local government content discovery – week 8</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/03/03/local-government-content-discovery-week-8.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Local government content discovery – week 8" /><published>2023-03-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-03-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/03/03/local-government-content-discovery-week-8</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/03/03/local-government-content-discovery-week-8.html"><![CDATA[<p>This was our 2nd to last week on this phase of the project. It’s fair to say that the past 8 weeks have flown by! We’ve started to shift our mindset from ‘making’ to ‘reflection’.</p>

<h2 id="testing-the-prototype-with-users">Testing the prototype with users</h2>

<p>During the past week we’ve held user research sessions with 6 users who are residents of the discovery local authorities.</p>

<p>As is so often the case with running user research sessions, they really helped us understand more about areas where we had questions, and also highlighted some things that we hadn’t considered.</p>

<p>We need to do some fuller analysis of the findings but here are some of the key headlines:</p>

<h3 id="clarity-on-why-certain-things-are-being-asked-for">Clarity on why certain things are being asked for</h3>

<p>In the prototype we ask for the start and end dates of the university or college course. It wasn’t immediately obvious why this information was needed or how it would be used. When asked, users assumed that this was to check whether they were a current student, but questioned the need to provide those dates.</p>

<p>Adding a short explanation within the ‘hint text’ might be something that helps.</p>

<h3 id="evidence-of-being-a-student">Evidence of being a student</h3>

<p>In the existing process users are asked to provide a copy of their student ID. We included this in the prototype.</p>

<p>Through the research we learnt that many universities provide a ‘statement of student status’ which may be a more appropriate thing to ask for. We’d recommend that this is an area to explore further should this work be carried forward.</p>

<h3 id="how-to-get-in-touch">How to get in touch</h3>

<p>An experience that many of the research participants expressed was a prior frustration with trying to find out the best way to get in touch with their local authority (although it is worth saying that the experiences were mostly positive once they found the right team or person).</p>

<p>On the confirmation page we suggest that they get in touch with the local authority should the user have any questions about their application. But we don’t provide information about how to make contact. This is partly due to it being a prototype, and built in a generic way to cover the 4 local authorities. However, given that this has been a pain point for many users any opportunity to add clarity here could prove helpful.</p>

<h3 id="opportunities-for-automation">Opportunities for automation</h3>

<p>Another consequence of this being a prototype (but still interesting to hear what users expect to happen) is around automation or linking together services.</p>

<p>Entering information manually when it could be pulled from somewhere else was a frustration. For addresses, although not flawless, postcode look-ups are a tried and tested pattern and could help make the service easier to use.</p>

<p>Another comment that we heard more than once was around why we asked for information about the property when a council tax account number had been provided – surely the council already had information about the property. In theory, yes you could potentially link these things together but there would need to be consideration to things like data privacy.</p>

<p>These aren’t quick fixes, but could form part of a longer term goal for council tax and other similar services.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/prototype-testing.png" alt="A screen shot of the mural board post user research feedback" /></p>

<h2 id="the-prototype-and-whats-next">The prototype (and what’s next)</h2>

<p>Now that we’ve completed the first round of user testing we’re happy to share a link to the prototype. You can access it using the link below, however please note if it hasn’t been accessed for a few hours then the server that it’s hosted on may take 10 to 15 minutes to wake up!</p>

<p>https://council-tax.onrender.com/</p>

<p>Alternatively, we’ve a recorded demo of the prototype that you can <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qKrvTTYN9PQ">watch here</a>.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qKrvTTYN9PQ?si=c86OasSxSzS9PROa" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h3 id="iterating">Iterating</h3>

<p>Based on findings from the user research we plan to make a few tweaks to the prototype. We won’t get an opportunity to test those changes with users, but we’re keen to show how user research can help you identify changes that you can make quickly to incrementally improve a service.</p>

<h2 id="content-request-workflows">Content request workflows</h2>

<p>We’ve heard from the local authorities how it is currently difficult to manage requests for content changes or publishing new content on the website. Typically someone will send an email but there is little information about what the content is for, or when it needs to go live.</p>

<p>We’ve been working on guidance around how to manage these requests through the use of a content request form (we’ll provide a link to that guidance shortly). To support this we’ve put together an example workflow that might help with both managing the requests whilst also providing visibility of which requests are being worked on.</p>

<p>You can access the example workflow through this Trello board, and if it’s useful please do make a copy and start using it yourself!</p>

<p>https://trello.com/b/9k38uMH8/example-content-design-triage-board</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/content-workflow.png" alt="A screen shot of content workflow board on Trello" /></p>

<h2 id="final-show-and-tell">Final show and tell</h2>

<p>Next week we’ll be holding our final show and tell on 9 March. We’ll provide an overview of what we did during the discovery, show findings from the user research, and talk through our recommendations for moving into alpha.</p>]]></content><author><name>matt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This was our 2nd to last week on this phase of the project. It’s fair to say that the past 8 weeks have flown by! We’ve started to shift our mindset from ‘making’ to ‘reflection’.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Local government content discovery – week 7</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/02/24/local-government-content-discovery-week-7.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Local government content discovery – week 7" /><published>2023-02-24T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-02-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/02/24/local-government-content-discovery-week-7</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/02/24/local-government-content-discovery-week-7.html"><![CDATA[<p>When we were planning out the work for scoping and building the council tax prototype we gave ourselves a couple of weeks for this work. However, we managed to get that everything we wanted to do wrapped up a bit quicker, this meant that over the past week we’ve had a slight change of focus ahead of a busy week 8 of user testing.</p>

<h2 id="documenting-what-weve-done">Documenting what we’ve done</h2>

<p>At the start of discovery one of the goals we set ourselves was to identify opportunities for practical changes to the ways of working within the local authorities when it comes to content workflows.</p>

<p>This week we were able to reflect on what we’ve learnt over the past 6 weeks and started gathering our thoughts on some proposed changes as well as recommendations for alpha.</p>

<h3 id="gathering-feedback">Gathering feedback</h3>

<p>Capturing user feedback from the website was something that came up during a few conversations. We’ve written up a guide for how to collect feedback along with some tips for how to analyse and use what you’ve learnt.</p>

<p>We’ve also created a template form with ideas for questions that might be useful to ask.</p>

<h3 id="prioritising-content-against-user-needs">Prioritising content against user needs</h3>

<p>Another challenge that we heard from each of the local authorities was that content was often added to the website without any consideration for its purpose.</p>

<p>We’ve written some guidelines for how and why a content request process might help to introduce thinking about what user needs are being met by new content being added to the website and to prioritising the work.</p>

<h3 id="extending-the-prototype">Extending the prototype</h3>

<p>We want to make sure that the prototype is able to live on past this phase of the project. All of the code is open source and lives in a public GitHub repository.</p>

<p>We’ve started writing up some high level instructions for how to spin up your version of the prototype and how to make changes to it.</p>

<h2 id="preparing-for-testing-the-prototype">Preparing for testing the prototype</h2>

<p>Next week we’ll be focusing on testing the prototype. We’ve got 9 sessions scheduled with residents across each of the 4 local authorities.</p>

<p>Whilst you can’t really hear from too many users 9 sessions is probably more than we’d normally expect to run at this stage, but given our time constraints this allows us to account for any potential ‘no shows’ or last minute cancellations.</p>

<h2 id="blogging-about-what-weve-done">Blogging about what we’ve done</h2>

<p>We’ve written a short blog post that describes why this discovery project came about and how we’ve gone about tackling the problem.</p>]]></content><author><name>matt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When we were planning out the work for scoping and building the council tax prototype we gave ourselves a couple of weeks for this work. However, we managed to get that everything we wanted to do wrapped up a bit quicker, this meant that over the past week we’ve had a slight change of focus ahead of a busy week 8 of user testing.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Local government content discovery – week 6</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/02/17/local-government-content-discovery-week-6.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Local government content discovery – week 6" /><published>2023-02-17T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-02-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/02/17/local-government-content-discovery-week-6</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/02/17/local-government-content-discovery-week-6.html"><![CDATA[<p>Our focus for this week has primarily been around building a prototype for the “check if you qualify for money off your council tax” and “apply for money off your council tax” journeys.</p>

<h2 id="mapping-out-the-flows">Mapping out the flows</h2>

<p>The user journey flows that we started last week were based on an amalgamation of some existing forms used by each of the four local authorities. This gave us a good baseline to work from and helped frame a conversation to validate the purpose of each question.</p>

<p>Working with Steph, our council tax subject matter expert, we were able to clarify why certain questions were needed and importantly we were able to remove some complexity by dropping questions that weren’t really required.</p>

<p>If we were doing this work as a part of an actual council tax transformation project we could have spent a lot more time on this and within the journeys we’ve looked at there’s definitely some complexity that we’ve purposely put aside. Maybe it’s something for the future!</p>

<h2 id="co-designing-the-content">Co-designing the content</h2>

<p>With a good understanding of what information was needed from a user our next step was to figure out the order in which to ask for that information and how to best phrase those questions. As we mentioned last week, the goal was to only ask for information that’s actually needed, no nice-to-have stuff, and to ask for the information in such a way that we’d be able to determine someone’s eligibility as early on in the journey as possible.</p>

<p>Gwen led a content co-design session with Carolyn, Louise, Tom and Adrián.</p>

<p>The conversation really highlighted the nuances around seemingly simple things like how to determine the number of people living at a property.</p>

<p>There was also the matter of how to ask about potentially sensitive circumstances such as when someone has recently died or when someone has separated from a partner.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/content-flows.png" alt="A screenshot of our content flows for the council tax prototype" /></p>

<p>There are definitely some bits to the journey where we still have questions, but the beauty of working in a fast and iterative way is that we don’t need to solve all the problems at once, we’ll learn through testing and figure out what needs to change. Don’t let <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perfect_is_the_enemy_of_good">perfect be the enemy of good</a> and all that!</p>

<h2 id="building-the-prototype">Building the prototype</h2>

<p>As the questions and flows started to take shape we were able to begin building out the prototype.</p>

<p>We wanted the prototype to be available online so that we could put it in front of potential users and just ‘real enough’ that it was something that people could relate to.</p>

<p>There are some harsh edges to the prototype which has allowed us to keep it focused on the part of the journey we’re working on. If it’s useful and if there’s appetite to do more work on council tax journeys the prototype can easily be extended.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/council-tax-prototype.gif" alt="An animated gif of the council tax prototype" /></p>

<p>Some minor tweaks aside, it’s in a good place to start testing with users. To avoid any spoilers to potential research participants we’ll share a link to the prototype after the next round of research.</p>

<h3 id="prototyping-toolkits">Prototyping toolkits</h3>

<p>There are lots of different tools that can be used to help with prototyping. For our purpose we opted to use a modified version of the <a href="https://prototype-kit.service.gov.uk/docs/">GOVUK prototype toolkit</a>. Our rationale for using this was:</p>

<ul>
  <li>the user interaction pattern for question branching (aka smart answers) has been tested many times over with users</li>
  <li>it’s well documented and there’s an active community of people using and maintaining the toolkit</li>
  <li>it’s easy to host somewhere online (we’ve used Render)</li>
  <li>there’s been extensive browser and device testing, so a reduced risk of web browser quirk tripping you up during user testing</li>
  <li>it’s possible to do some subtle re-theming</li>
</ul>

<p>On the point of re-theming, we made use of the modified toolkit from the Learn by making project. It’s open source and available in a <a href="https://github.com/learnbymakingwales/lbm-prototype-kit">public code repository</a> — another win for working in the open.</p>

<p>We’ve made the code for the council tax prototype open too, so having said that we won’t share the URL to the clickable prototype just yet, if you really want to take a look <a href="https://github.com/learnbymakingwales/council-tax-prototype">under the hood</a> here you go!</p>]]></content><author><name>matt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our focus for this week has primarily been around building a prototype for the “check if you qualify for money off your council tax” and “apply for money off your council tax” journeys.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Local government content discovery – week 4 and 5</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/02/10/local-government-content-discovery-week-4-and-5.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Local government content discovery – week 4 and 5" /><published>2023-02-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-02-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/02/10/local-government-content-discovery-week-4-and-5</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/02/10/local-government-content-discovery-week-4-and-5.html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been a busy couple of weeks. So much so that I completely forgot to publish the week 4 notes and left them sat in draft. This week’s update will cover the past two weeks</p>

<h2 id="hearing-from-more-users">Hearing from more users</h2>

<p>We wrapped up the first round of user research with a couple more interviews with residents from within the local authority areas. As ever it’s incredibly powerful to see people’s experience using your service. There is always something to learn no matter how good the service is. It reminds me of this drawing from <a href="https://twitter.com/psd">Paul Downey</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/user-testing-bitter-sweet-sorrow.jpg" alt="A paul downey doodle about user testing being such sweet sorrow" /></p>

<p><em>https://www.flickr.com/photos/psd/8593491874/in/photolist-2m1p49e-eR12Nw-e6nTK1</em></p>

<p>We’ll be doing another round of user research where we hope to show users a prototype that we’ve built.</p>

<h2 id="getting-together-in-newport">Getting together in Newport</h2>

<p>At the start of week 4 we got together in Newport for a day of workshopping. Not only was it great to meet people in person, we covered a lot of things and left with plenty to think about.</p>

<p>The focus for the morning was on the topic of council tax, and during the afternoon we changed gears and looked at the respective publishing workflows for each local authority.</p>

<h3 id="user-needs-and-prioritisation">User needs and prioritisation</h3>
<p>We spent some time as a group writing and prioritising user needs. We started fairly broadly, before focusing more specifically on the area of council tax discounts. It was useful to help us think about the user needs that had the highest value vs demand.</p>

<p>It was also useful to help us decide that for the purpose of prototyping we should focus on single person discounts and student discounts, both have complexity with the language used and provide opportunities for us to improve.</p>

<h2 id="midpoint-show-and-tell">Midpoint show and tell</h2>
<p>On Thursday (9th) we held a ‘midpoint’ show and tell. This was a good opportunity to invite a slightly broader audience than our regular weekly show and tells. It allowed us to recap and reflect on the work we’ve done so far.</p>

<p>The feedback we received was really encouraging and it was good to hear that other local authorities also recognised and faced similar challenges around writing content for users. Hopefully the work we’re doing will be of value to organisations outside of the four that we’re working directly with.</p>

<p>Our next public-ish show and tell is on March 9th at 11am. If you’d like to be invited please do let us know!</p>

<h2 id="user-journey-mapping">User journey mapping</h2>

<p>As we’ve previously mentioned, we’re using council tax as an area to focus on. We quickly found that council tax itself has so much complexity to it and is such a broad topic. We’ve decided to narrow the focus further to council tax discounts and exemptions, and to be even more specific – single person discounts and student exemptions.</p>

<p>Our plan is to prototype around the following user needs:</p>

<p><strong>As a</strong> person who lives alone
<strong>I want</strong> to check whether I qualify for a council tax discount
<strong>So that</strong> I can reduce my council tax bill</p>

<p>And;</p>

<p><strong>As a</strong> student
<strong>I want</strong> to check whether I qualify for an exemption on paying council tax
<strong>So that</strong> I can lower my monthly outgoings</p>

<p>If we have time then we’ll also look at the journey to apply for the respective discount and exemption.</p>

<p>As a starting point we’ve begun to map out the potential user journeys. These are very much work in-progress and the order of the steps and the language used will be refined during some co-design sessions we’re running next week.</p>

<p>Our goal is to only ask for information that is needed to firstly determine whether someone qualifies for a discount or exemption, and then to apply. When someone isn’t eligible we want to try and determine that as soon as possible.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/council-tax-journey-maps.png" alt="A screen shot of the council tax journey maps" /></p>

<p>For a larger version of the journey map, <a href="https://docs.google.com/drawings/d/1D3U6eLtDBgCaTVioa3jtGpc6a81hbxn-O4rXn56vtEA/edit?usp=sharing">click here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="exploring-options-for-prototyping">Exploring options for prototyping</h2>
<p>We’re delighted that <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/lcollinsdesigner">Liam Collins</a> has joined the team to help us with the prototyping side of things. Our goal is to have something that we can spin up pretty quickly and is easy to update. The prototype doesn’t need to be super high fidelity, but enough that we can test the content the journey flows with users.</p>

<p>Our instinct is that the <a href="https://docs.publishing.service.gov.uk/repos/smart-answers.html">GOV.UK smart answers</a> are a good candidate for experimenting with. Liam has been looking at options for hosting a version of the GOVUK prototype toolkit that we can subtly re-theme.</p>]]></content><author><name>matt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s been a busy couple of weeks. So much so that I completely forgot to publish the week 4 notes and left them sat in draft. This week’s update will cover the past two weeks]]></summary></entry></feed>